A Guide to the Annexation Case Files of the Commission on Local Government, 1960-2001.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Local Government, Commission on, Annexation Case Files
1960-2001.
The Library of Virginia
32000, 32802, 32990, 33034, 33418, 33427, 34089, 34583, 34594, 35016
Virginia. Commission on Local Government.
93.2 cu. ft.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Commission on Local Government was created February 28, 1979, by an act of the General Assembly, and formally began operation in January, 1980. It was created at the urging of a joint Virginia Municipal League-Virginia Association of Counties task force studying annexation and boundary change laws. The Commission originally was placed under the Secretary of Commerce and Resources, and on June 7, 1983 under the Secretary of Administration and Finance. Effective July 1, 1984, the secretariats divided, and the Commission was placed under the authority of the Secretary of Administration.
The Commission's major activities include assisting in the mediation and negotiated settlement of local boundary change and governmental transition issues; reviewing proposed annexations, petitions for partial county immunity from annexation, voluntary boundary adjustments, town incorporations, town or county transitions city transitions to town status, and interlocal agreements relative to such issues, and rendering findings of fact and recommendations to the affected local governments and to the courts; assisting local governmental issues, upon request, in the investigation and analysis of other local governmental issues; developing fiscal impact statements for submission to the General Assembly on all legislation introduced which may require one or more local governments to establish a new or expand an existing public service (State and Federal mandates); undertaking comparative analysis of local fiscal conditions; providing a liaison service between the state and its localities relative to annexation issues. The Commission consists of five members who are appointed by the governor and confirmed by the General Assembly for five-year terms, with the term of one member expiring each year, subject to reappointment. Reports on annexation actions, settlement agreements, and agreements defining annexation rights are published as developed, and fiscal issues are addressed in "Comparative Revenue Capacity, Revenue Effort, and Fiscal Stress of Virginia's Counties and Cities, 1985/86 and 1986/87," prepared for the General Assembly.
he staff of the Commission provides assistance to the Local Government Advisory Council. This body, which was established by statute in 1978, serves as a forum for the discussion of state-local issues and other governmental concerns in the commonwealth. The chairman of the Council is the governor, other members are the lieutenant governor, executive directors of the Virginia Municipal League and the Virginia Association of Counties, and 22 members of local governing bodies throughout Virginia representing each of Virginia's 22 planning districts. In 1990, the Local Government Advisory Council was reorganized and was renamed the Virginia Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations. The reorganization of this body included a reduction in size, reconfigured to include six legislators, a private citizen, and a member of a regional planning district. Other changes included the method of appointment, schedule of elections, and the number of meetings required. Pursuant to Chapter 55, 2004 Virginia Acts of Assembly, the Virginia Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations was abolished effective July 1, 2004.
The Commission on Local Government was abolished as a separate agency by an act of the General Assembly in 2003, and on June 16, 2003, the Commission on Local Government was placed within the Dept. of Housing and Community Development.
Scope and Content
The case files contain exhibit material submitted by the parties involved in the annexation and boundary change proceedings and copies of other materials and data requested by the Commission. Included are copies of documents relating to local government operations (budgets, financial statements, ordinances, regulations), agreements, depositions, petitions, plans (comprehensive, feasibility, etc.), reports, tapes and transcripts of public and Commission hearings, maps, photographs, census data, and incoming correspondence and memoranda. A bibliography of exhibits and related material is prepared by Commission staff for each case. Some of the records in this series pre-date the creation of he Commission on Local Government.
Arranged by case file.
Acquisition Information
Accession 32000 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, February 23, 1984.
Accession 32802 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, August 15, 1986.
Accession 32990 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, June 24, 1987.
Accession 34034 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, December 10, 1987.
Accession 33418 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, February 23, 1989.
Accession 33427 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, April 4, 1989.
Accession 34089 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, February 20, 1992.
Accession 34583 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, January 12, 1994.
Accession 34594 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, March 7, 1994.
Accession 35016 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, February 13, 1995.
Contents List
- Annexation case files, 1980-1983 (Accession 32000)., Extent: 22.4 cubic feet (16 boxes)
  - Kenbridge - Lunenburg County, 1981. (Box 1)
  - Harrisonburg - Rockingham County, 1980-1981. (Box 2)
  - Enporia - Greensville County, 1980-1983. (Box 3)
  - Luray - Page County, 1982-1983. (Box 4)
  - Buena Vista - Rockbridge County, 1980-1983. (Box 5)
  - Williamsburg - James City County, 1980-1983. (Box 6)
  - Fredericksburg - Spotsylvania County, 1981-1982. (Box 7a)
  - Fredericksburg - Spotsylvania County, 1981-1982. (Box 7b)
  - Federicksburg - Spotsylvania County, 1981-1982. (Box 7c)
  - Leesburg - Loudoun County, 1981-1983. (Box 8)
  - Staunon / Waynesboro - Augusta County, 1980-1982. (Box 9)
  - Harrisonburg - Rockingham County, 1980-1981. (Box 10)
  - Staunton / Waynesboro - Augusta County, 1980-1982. (Box 11)
  - Staunton / Waynesboro - Augusta County, 1980-1982. (Box 12)
  - Staunton / Waynesboro - Augusta County, 1980-1982. (Box 13)
  - Staunton / Waynesboro - Augusta County, 1980-1982. (Box 14)
- Annexation case files, 1984-1985 (Accession 32802)., Extent: 25 cubic feet (25 boxes)
  - Bridgewater - Rockingham County, 1984-1985. (Box 1)
  - Clintwood - Dickinson County, 1984-1985. (Box 1)
  - Bluefield - Tazewell County, 1984-1985. (Box 2)
  - Lynchburg - Campbell County, 1984-1985. (Box 3)
  - Emporia - Greensville Couny, 1984-1985. (Box 4)
  - Strasburg - Shenandoah County, 1984-1985. (Box 4)
  - Radford - Montgomery County, 1984-1985. (Box 5)
  - Staunton - Augusta County, 1984-1985. (Box 6)
  - Lexington - Rockbridge County, 1984-1985. (Box 6)
  - Waynesboro - Augusta County, 1984-1985. (Box 7)
  - Waynesboro - Augusta County, 1984-1985. (Box 8)
  - Covington / Clifton Forge - Alleghany County, 1984-1985. (Box 9)
  - Franklin - Southampton County / Isle of Wight County, 1984-1985. (Box 10)
  - Covington - Alleghany County, 1984-1985. (Box 11)
  - Covington - Alleghany County, 1984-1985. (Box 12)
  - Covington - Alleghany County, 1984-1985. (Box 13)
  - Staunton - Augusta County, 1984-1985. (Box 14)
  - Abingdon - Washington County, 1984-1985. (Box 15)
  - Abingdon - Washington County, 1984-1985. (Box 16)
  - Lexington - Rockbridge County, 1984-1985. (Box 16)
  - Lexington - Rockbridge County, 1984-1985. (Box 17)
  - Lexington - Rockbridge County, 1984-1985. (Box 18)
  - Danville - Pittsylvania County, 1984-1985. (Box 19)
  - Danville - Pittsylvania County, 1984-1985. (Box 20)
  - Danville - Pittsylvania County, 1984-1985. (Box 21)
  - Danville - Pittsylvania County, 1984-1985. (Box 22)
  - Danville - Pittsylvania County, 1984-1985. (Box 23)
  - Danville - Pittsylvania County, 1984-1985. (Box 24)
  - Danville - Pittsylvania County (Oversize), 1984-1985. (Box 25b)
- Annexation case files, 1984-1987 (Accession 32990)., Extent: 7 cubic feet (7 boxes)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell - Prince George County, 1984-1987. (Box 25)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell - Prince George County, 1984-1987. (Box 26)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell - Prince George County, 1984-1987. (Box 27)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell - Prince George County, 1984-1987. (Box 28)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell - Prince George County, 1984-1987. (Box 29)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell - Prince George County, 1984-1987. (Box 30)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell - Prince George County, 1984-1987. (Box 31)
  - Warsaw - Richmond County, 1985-1986. (Box 31)
- Annexation case files, 1986-1987 (Accession 33034)., Extent: 9 cubic feet (9 boxes)
  - Lebanon - Russell County, 1987. (Box 32)
  - Salem - Roanoke County, 1987. (Box 32)
  - Herndon - Fairfax County, 1987. (Box 33)
  - Christiansburg - Montgomery County, 1987. (Box 33)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell - Prince George County, 1986-1987. (Box 34)
  - Various cases - Oversize, 1986-1987. (Box 34b)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell - Prince George County, 1986-1987. (Box 35)
  - Christiansburg - Montgomery County, 1986-1987. (Box 36)
  - Christiansburg - Montgomery County, 1986-1987. (Box 37)
  - Christiansburg - Montgomery County, 1986-1987. (Box 38)
  - Christiansburg - Montgomery County, 1986-1987. (Box 39)
- Annexation case files, 1988 (Accession 33418)., Extent: 2 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  - Danville - Pittsylvania County, 1988. (Box 40)
  - Berryville - Clarke County, 1988. (Box 40)
  - Berryville - Clarke County, 1988. (Box 41)
- Annexation case files, 1960-1970 (Accession 33427)., Extent: 5 cubic feet (5 boxes and 3 volumes)
  - Richmond - Henrico County, 1960-1970. (Box 42)
  - Richmond - Henrico County, 1960-1970. (Box 43)
  - Richmond - Henrico County, 1960-1970. (Box 44)
  - Richmond - Henrico County, 1960-1970. (Box 45)
  - Richmond - Henrico County, 1960-1970. (Box 46)
  - Falls Church - Fairfax County, 1960-1970. (Box 46)
  - Richmond - Henrico County, 1960-1970. (Box 1)
  - Richmond - Henrico County, 1960-1970. (Box 2)
  - Richmond - Henrico County, 1960-1970. (Box 3)
- Annexation case files, 1971-1991 (Accession 34089)., Extent: 9 cubic feet (9 boxes)
  - Chincoteague - Accomack County, 1971-1991. (Box 47)
  - Wytheville - Wythe County, 1971-1991. (Box 47)
  - Wytheville - Wythe County, 1971-1991. (Box 48)
  - Manassas Park - Prince William County, 1971-1991. (Box 48)
  - Manassas Park - Prince William County, 1971-1991. (Box 49)
  - Broadway - Rockingham County, 1971-1991. (Box 49)
  - Dayton - Rockingham County, 1971-1991. (Box 49)
  - Chatham - Pittsylvania County, 1971-1991. (Box 50)
  - Orange - Orange County, 1971-1991. (Box 50)
  - Clifton Forge - Alleghany County, 1971-1991. (Box 51)
  - Clifton Forge - Alleghany County, 1971-1991. (Box 52)
  - Detch / Williamsburg - York County, 1971-1991. (Box 52)
  - Crown American / Bristol - Washington County, 1971-1991. (Box 53)
  - Carriage Hill / Bedford - Bedford County, 1971-1991. (Box 53)
  - Cape Charles - Northampton County, 1971-1991. (Box 54)
  - Cape Charles - Northampton County, 1971-1991. (Box 55)
- Annexation case files, 1991-1992 (Accession 34583)., Extent: 5 cubic feet (5 boxes)
  - South Boston - Halifax County, 1991-1992. (Box 56)
  - South Boston - Halifax County, 1991-1992. (Box 57)
  - Farmville - Prince Edward County, 1991-1992. (Box 58)
  - Radford - Montgomery County, 1991-1992. (Box 59)
  - Bedford - Bedford County, 1991-1992. (Box 60)
  - Amherst - Amherst County, 1991-1992. (Box 60)
- Annexation case files, 1991-1994 (Accession 34594)., Extent: 4 cubic feet (4 boxes)
  - Colonial Beach - Westmoreland County, 1991-1994. (Box 61)
  - Colonial Beach - Westmoreland County, 1991-1994. (Box 62)
  - Purcellville - Loudoun County, 1991-1994. (Box 62)
  - Wright Raspberry Ridge / Purcellville - Loudoun County, 1991-1994. (Box 63)
  - Wright Raspberry Ridge / Purcellville - Loudoun County, 1991-1994. (Box 64)
- Annexation case files, 1993-1996 (Accession 35016)., Extent: 5 cubic feet (5 boxes)
  - Hillsville - Carroll County, 1993-1996. (Box 65)
  - Hillsville - Carroll County, 1993-1996. (Box 66)
  - Ashland - Hanover County, 1993-1996. (Box 67)
  - Ashland - Hanover County, 1993-1996. (Box 68)
  - Hillsville - Carroll County, 1993-1996. (Box 68)
  - Bedford - Bedford County, 1993-1996. (Box 68)
  - Winchester - Frederick County, 1993-1996. (Box 69)